Guide to the New-York Historical Society Vertical Files, circa 1970s-circa 2015, PM 2
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society vertical files
circa 1970s-circa 2015
New-York Historical Society
PM 2
8 Linear feet in 8 record cartons.
Subject files on topics of regional interest created and maintained by New-York Historical Society Library staff as a source of ready reference for frequently asked questions. The files consist largely of photocopied clippings from the New York Times.
Access Restrictions
This collection is stored offsite. To arrange to consult it, please go to www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged alphabetically by file title in boxes 1-7. Box 8 contains miscellaneous material that is not part of the collection proper, but was stored with it in the same filing cabinet before the collection was transferred to boxes and shipped offsite.
Historical note
Before the internet transformed the way researchers access information, libraries routinely maintained collections of vertical files—ready reference material such as newspaper clippings, brochures, and other ephemera—on various topics of interest, arranged by subject. The name "vertical file" stems from how these collections were commonly stored, in vertical-style filing cabinets.
Scope and Contents
The New-York Historical Society Vertical Files is an artificial collection begun by the N-YHS reference librarians, probably in the 1970s, and maintained and expanded through about 2015. The bulk of the collection consists of photocopied newspaper articles—mostly from the New York Times but also from other area papers—on various topics of regional interest that were frequently requested by researchers who visited or contacted the library. While much of the content of the files is now readily available online, the physical copies provide the ease of ready reference by grouping together numerous pieces on a single subject. See the inventory of this finding aid for a complete list of topics.
Ephemera.; Newspaper clippings.; Vertical files.; Libraries -- Special collections -- Reference sources.; New York (N.Y.) -- History.; New York (State) -- History.
- Artists (Offsite-box 1)
- Audubon, John James (Offsite-box 1)
- General Slocum Disaster (Offsite-box 1)
- Hussar (ship) (Offsite-box 1)
- Loyalist Gazette (Offsite-box 1)
- Lewis, Morgan (Offsite-box 1)
- Lighthouses (Offsite-box 1)
- Moore, Clement Clarke (Offsite-box 1)
- New Jersey (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—African Americans (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—African Americans—biography (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—African Americans—communities (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—African Americans—enslavement (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—African Americans—festivals (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—African Americans—research (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—African Americans—Underground Railroad (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—airports (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—animals (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—archaeology (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—architects (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—armories (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—art and artists (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—asylums (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—baseball (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—baths and pools (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—breweries (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—bridges (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—bridges—Brooklyn Bridge (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—buildings—banks (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—buildings—cast iron (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—buildings—convention centers, arenas (Offsite-box 1)
- New York City—buildings—decoration and ornament (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—dwellings (divided by location) (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—dwellings—apartment houses (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—dwellings—research (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—educational institutions (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—factories and warehouses (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—foreign consulates, cultural centers (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—historic houses—Gracie Mansion (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—historic houses—Morris-Jumel Mansion (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—historic houses—Fraunces Tavern (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—office buildings (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—office buildings—Chrysler (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—office buildings—Empire State (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—office buildings—Flatiron (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—office buildings—Woolworth (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—public buildings (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—public buildings—City Hall (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—public buildings—Custom House (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—restoration and rehabilitation (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—stables and garages (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—studios (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—terminals (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—terminals—Grand Central Terminal (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buildings—terminals—Pennsylvania Station (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—buses (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—businesses (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—celebrities (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—cemeteries (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—cemeteries—African Burial Ground (Offsite-box 2)
- New York City—charities (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—churches, synagogues (divided by borough) (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—circuses (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—city planning (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—clocks (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—clubs (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—clubs—Aldine (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—crime (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—elevated railroads (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—environmental issues (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—fairs (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—ferries (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—fires and fire prevention (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—folklore (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—food & drink (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—fortification (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—fountains (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—furniture makers (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—galleries (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—gardens (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—gays (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—harbor, Gateway (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—highways (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—history (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—history—colonial (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—history—consolidation (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—history—Revolution (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—history—Revolution—Evacuation Day (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—history—Revolution—Nathan Hale Story (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—history—1775-1865 (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—holidays (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—hospitals (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—hotels, taverns (Offsite-box 3)
- New York City—immigration (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—Indians of North America (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—Landmarks Preservation (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—libraries (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—lighting (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—literary landmarks (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—maps (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—markets (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—mayors (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—medicine (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—miscellaneous (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—murals (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—museums (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—museums—N-YHS (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—music (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—names (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—names—Big Apple (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—National Archives (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—natural history (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—newspapers (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—nightclubs (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—parades (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—parks (Offsite-box 4)
- New York City—parks—Central Park (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—parks—High Line (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—photography (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—playgrounds (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—police (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—recreation (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—restaurants, bars, taverns (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—rivers (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—sections—Battery Park (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—sections—Bowery (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—sections—Bronx (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—sections—Brooklyn (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—sections—Brooklyn—Coney Island (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—sections—Chelsea (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—sections—Chinatown (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—sections—Clinton (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—sections—Diamond District (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—sections—East Harlem (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—sections—East Side (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—sections—East Village (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—sections—Garment Center (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—sections—Gramercy Park (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—sections—Greenwich Village (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—sections—Harlem (Offsite-box 5)
- New York City—sections—Islands (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Islands—Roosevelt (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Ladies' Mile (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Little Italy (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Lower East Side (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Lower Manhattan (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Midtown (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Murray Hill (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Noho (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Queens (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Soho (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Staten Island (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Stuyvesant Square (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Times Square (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Tribeca (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Turtle Bay (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Union Square (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Upper East Side (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Upper West Side (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Washington Heights (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—sections—Yorkville (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—signs (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—social life and customs (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—statues and monuments (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—statues and monuments—Civic Fame (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—statues and monuments—Columbus Monument (Offsite-box 6)
- New York City—stores (Offsite-box 7)
- New York City—street commerce, pushcarts, peddlers, etc. (Offsite-box 7)
- New York City—streets (Offsite-box 7)
- New York City—streets (sidewalks) (Offsite-box 7)
- New York City—subways (Offsite-box 7)
- New York City—subways—Second Avenue subway (Offsite-box 7)
- New York City—subway stations (Offsite-box 7)
- New York City—taxis (Offsite-box 7)
- New York City—terrorism (Offsite-box 7)
- New York City—theaters (Offsite-box 7)
- New York City—tokens (Offsite-box 7)
- New York City—traffic (Offsite-box 7)
- New York City—transportation (Offsite-box 7)
- New York City—trees (Offsite-box 7)
- New York City—trolleys (Offsite-box 7)
- New York City—tunnels (Offsite-box 7)
- New York City—wards (Offsite-box 7)
- New York City—water, misc. (Offsite-box 7)
- New York City—water supply (Offsite-box 7)
- New York City—waterfronts (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—buildings (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—canals (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—constitution (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—counties—Albany (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—counties—Chautauqua (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—counties—Columbia (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—counties—Dutchess (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—counties—Greene (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—counties—Herkimer (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—counties—Madison (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—counties—Nassau and Suffolk (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—counties—Niagara (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—counties—Orange (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—counties—Putnam (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—counties—Rockland (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—counties—Seneca (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—counties—Ulster (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—counties—Westchester (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—farms (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—history (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—Hudson River (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—Lake Champlain (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—National Register of Historic Places (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—resorts (Offsite-box 7)
- New York State—song (Offsite-box 7)
- Orphan trains (Offsite-box 7)
- U.S.—Constitution (Offsite-box 7)
- Miscellaneous—Arthur Marks tours (Offsite-box 8)
- Miscellaneous—Exhibits—Epidemics (M. Carey, Proposed) (Offsite-box 8)
- Miscellaneous—Christopher Gray—Streetscapes (Offsite-box 8)
- Miscellaneous—Clement Clarke Moore exhibit (Offsite-box 8)
- Miscellaneous—Clippings, miscellaneous 19th century (Offsite-box 8)
- Miscellaneous—Constitution (Offsite-box 8)
- Miscellaneous—Hamilton NY Post N-YHS Clippings August 1993- (Offsite-box 8)
- Miscellaneous—Hamilton New York Post 2004 photocopies (Offsite-box 8)
- Miscellaneous—July 9, 1776 (Offsite-box 8)
- Miscellaneous—Maps—NYC (Offsite-box 8)
- Miscellaneous—To Preserve a Heritage: The Restoration and Utilization of Historic Sites in Lower Manhattan (Offsite-box 8)
- Miscellaneous—Treasury of the Past 1995 (Offsite-box 8)
- Miscellaneous—Treasury of the past 1955 labels (Offsite-box 8)
- Miscellaneous—Victorian Pleasures: Nineteenth Century American Board and Table Games from the Liman Collection (2 copies) (Offsite-box 8)
- Miscellaneous—Words and Music: Sheet Music of Not so Long Ago (Offsite-box 8)